Inventory of the Igor' Alekseevich Mikhaĭlov collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Igor' Alekseevich Mikhaĭlov collection
1962-2003
2008C30
Mikhaĭlov, Igor' Alekseevich
3 manuscript boxes (1.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Mikhaĭlov collection is comprised of pamphlets, leaflets, flyers, serial issues, circulated material, and photocopies of government documents, relating to post-Soviet politics in Russia, Moldova and Abkhazia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
After the fall of the Soviet Union, Igor' Mikhaĭlov served as the representative of the Dniester Moldovan Republic to Moscow. In the mid-1990s, he worked for the Russian Deputy Prime Minister Valery Serov. Since retiring from government work, Mikhailov has been a journalist and political analyst.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Igor' Alekseevich Mikhaĭlov collection documents post-Soviet independence movements in Abkhazia and Moldova as well as political developments in the Russian federation during Boris Yeltsin's presidency.
The Abkhazia file includes printed matter and serial issues on the Georgian conflict and Abkhaz national identity. Many pamphlets, such as Abkhaziia: ne Gruziia, advocate independence from Georgia. This series also contains a reprinted interview with the former president of Abkhazia, Vladislav Ardzinba.
Of particular note in the Moldova file are photographs and documents pertaining to the Dniester Moldovan Republic (Transdniestria), which declared independence in 1990. In addition to newspapers, political flyers and government documents, there are accounts of violence against civilians collected by the Association of Women of Moldova.
The RSFSR and Russian Federation file includes documents on economic development and CIS integration after the fall of the Soviet Union. The bulk of the series consists of Duma decrees from 1999 to 2002.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Moldova--Politics and government--1991-; Abkhaziia (Georgia); Georgia (Republic)--Politics and government--1991-
Collection Contents
- Abkhazia file, 1989-2000; 1-2 (Box 1-2:)
  Includes newspapers, pamphlets, research materials and correspondence relating to post-Soviet nation-building and the conflict with Georgia. Arranged by document type and ordered chronologically.
  - Newspapers, 1989-2000 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1992-1999 (Folder 1: 2-3)
    Includes Belaia kniga Abkhazii, Abkhaziia ne Gruziia and Voĭna protiv Abkhaziia. In English, Russian and Georgian
  - Letter from Taras Shamba, World Congress of Abkhazian-Abazian People, 14 June 1993 (Folder 1: 4)
    Includes constitution of Abkhazia
  - Research materials, 1995-1998 (Folder 1: 5)
    Includes journals and reprinted articles
  - Printed matter, 1994-1996 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes flyers, decals, calendars, brochures and pins
- Moldova file, 1962-1998 (Box 2:)
  Contains newspapers, pamphlets, government documents, photographs and research materials relating to politics in Moldova, particularly in the Dniester Moldovan Republic. Arranged by document type and ordered chronologically.
  - Pamphlets, 1962-1991 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Gagauz Autonomous Republic, 1989 (Folder 2: 3)
    Pamphlets related to the founding of an autonomous republic in the Moldavian SSR
  - Dniester Moldovan Republic, 1989-1997
    - Newspapers, 1989-1992 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Government documents, 1990-1996 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Photographs, 1992 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Letter to Igor' Mikhaĭlov, 1992 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Witness accounts, 1992 (Folder 2: 8)
      Reports on violence in the Dniester Moldovan Republic collected by the Association of Women in Moldova
    - Clippings, 1992 (Folder 2: 9)
      Includes articles about Russian troops in Moldova
    - Pamphlets, 1992-1997 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Vasile Nedelciuc papers, 1996-1997 (Folder 2: 11)
    Includes a letter and reprinted articles by the Moldovan politician
  - Parliamentary elections, 1997-1998 (Folder 2: 12)
- RSFSR and Russian Federation file, 1975-2003; 2-3 (Box 2-3:)
  Consists of pamphlets, government publications, decrees, maps and photographs relating to post-Soviet politics in Russia. Arranged by subject and ordered chronologically.
  - Aleksandr Gavrilovich Lun'kov files, 1975-1989 (Folder 2: 13)
    Travel documents for the Soviet journalist
  - "O nauchnykh i propagandistskikh meropriiatiiakh v sviazi s 50-letiem vkhozhdeniia Latvii, Litvy i Estonii v sostav SSSR," pamphlet, 6 June 1989 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Congress of People's Deputies pamphlets and speeches, June 1990-September 1993 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Igor' Mikhaĭlov personal files, 1991-1996 (Folder 3: 1)
    Includes correspondence with Hoover Archives, photocopies of arrest records and a currency collection
  - "Window of Opportunity: Joint Program for Western Cooperation in the Soviet Transformation to Democracy and the Market Economy," Graham Allison and Grigoriĭ Iavlinskiĭ, Harvard University, June 29, 1991 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Economic reforms research materials, 1992-1993 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Presidential decrees, 1992-1994 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Government publications, 1993-1996 (Folder 3: 5)
    Includes "Parlamentskaia nedelia" and "Pravitel'skiĭ vestnik"
  - Photographs, circa 1990s (Folder 3: 6)
    Includes photograph of anti-Yeltsin protest
  - Maps, circa 1990s (Folder 3: 7)
    Includes troop movements in Tajikistan
  - Electoral materials, 1995-1998 (Folder 3: 8)
    Includes pro-Luzhkov and anti-Yeltsin flyers
  - Civil society documents, 1996 (Folder 3: 9)
    Includes documents on accreditation of journalists
  - Ukraine relations government documents, 1996 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Economic Integration in the Commonwealth of Independent States, 1996-1997 (Folder 3: 11)
    Includes government documents on economic planning and development
  - Mezhdunarodnaia assotsiatsiia fondov mira, 1997 (Folder 3: 12)
    Includes publications on relations between Russian and NATO and CIS integration
  - Report on the Moscow Patriarchate and the Roman Catholic Church, Georgiĭ Ziablintsev, 1997 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Belarus relations documents and newspapers, 1997 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Duma decrees, 1999-2002 (Folder 3: 15-16)
    Includes laws on borders, pensions, rights of national minorities, terrorism, Eurasian economic cooperation, chemical weapons, and Baikonur